So.
Good afternoon everyone.
Welcome to the first class for dedicated
to exercise a little bit and practice.
With the the help of AI to try to
together,
I I remember to everyone that this is an
experiment and you're part of the
experiment.
It is an experimental course where we are
trying to introduce the AI as much as
possible, not because we are,
because there are there is evidence,
strong evidence.
I want to show you.
A post that I read today.
Um.
We have to redesign the way we teach
programming and the use of programming
skills in the real world is changing so.
Cursor.
How many of you are aware of Cursor?
So Cursor is basically an online platform
for software development.
Guess what? With the A I is super popular.
They were on the announcement of GPT 5.
So it is that they are partnering with
Open A I.
And by the way,
if you are not on LinkedIn,
it's a good idea to enroll.
Anita Molik is someone which is worth
following and.
Codex is similar,
so proactive agents which code on your
behalf.
Adopters produced 39% more code merges
with no sign of decreasing quality.
Revert rates where the same bugs dropped,
so less bugs, same revert, so rollback.
And no sign that the scope of the work
track.
So that's a number which is already in
the past. OK,
so real world is moving faster and it's
moving with the eye.
Working on our behalf if you browse.
Uh, when it is up.
If you have a a rep on GitHub,
you will see that there are a number of.
Um.
No, not both.
I know.
Not here. Uh, or.
So um.
You get a pull request generated by
agents that suggest you automatically to
change the version of our software,
et cetera.
And typically this is the dependency
agent.
And the the bot helps you and say, OK,
this is the way.
So this is just to say again,
this AI thing is part of your future for
sure.
Also of mine, for sure of yours. OK,
so uh.
Apparently you have to pass an exam at
the end of the course and the number of
questions around the project is
increasing, is rising in numbers, so.
Uh.
There will be another exam first.
Also because it's apparently it's
impossible to tell whether some project
has been made by you or by the eye,
and so now oral exam is mandatory because
it's the only way we can check whether
you learn or the eye learned.
The contact.
Um.
I I always think that projects are also a
moment of growth, personal growth.
So the idea is for you to explore.
Some area of PROGRAMMING languages,
complex systems and many other things
using the A I.
And so in this respect it's mandatory the
fact that you use some A I system of your.
Choice.
I remind you that if you log in into
office.com.
All of you have the web AI.
A system which is not as good as GPT,
but it works and it uses GPT4 and five as
models.
So basically the the the basis is that
one, but if you like to.
Try yourself and use GPTOSS on your
laptop. That would be interesting too.
So I mean choosing the model is part of
the exercise.
If you want to try to run on premise so
in your laptop I will suggest you to
install Ollama.
And in general install OLAMA and learn
how to use it because they will.
It is already big and it's growing bigger
is 1.
So in the open source space there is
OLAMA is a.
Unimportant it it it is basically a
common line tool with a now also with a
web UI so you can get an assistant which
runs locally and a number of models that
plus.
Uh.
The models available on a game face that
allows you to run local AI.
So it it is clearly something that if you
don't, you must become familiar with.
There are interesting models.
So there is for instance, for instance,
there is the Code Llama, which is a model.
Training for programming,
there is a SQL coder which is dedicated
to SQL.
Statements and database analysis.
So there are a lot of these things.
Another interesting.
Project is cohere.
So.
Oh.
I'm not getting the.
I mean if you if you search you will find
also let me check GitHub.
Uh.
So here we are.
So this is a full platform to create AI
agents capable of running on premises,
so not using online models.
So all these clearly.
Uh, our elements uh uh.
That uh may uh.
May be interesting as the model.
So basically in general whenever you do
something with the eye,
the first question is which would what is
the the model you're going to use and
model makes the difference.
Uh,
just this morning I was reading another.
Uh.
What's up? What is it?
There we are awesome.
Where he was commenting the recently
received released the GPT 5.
1 and it basically complaints about the
fact that they introduced the.
The personality in the assistant,
but actually depend according to the
personality you will get different
answers.
OK. And he says, I mean,
I I don't want a friend, a Paul,
an AI Paul.
I I I only need a business system which
works and the fact that the system gives
different answers depending on the
personality.
It may be a threat.
So that's an interesting angle.
So going back to the project,
the project basically is meant for you to
test your skills that hopefully you learn.
In this beautiful course. Um.
Around PROGRAMMING languages.
So there will be a number of assignments
that in full transparency we will
generate with AI,
which is fairly good given a number of
examples to generalize and give you some
other similar.
Uh, that will require you to um.
Deepen your understanding of a specific,
possibly unknown angle of PROGRAMMING
language or systems in in the in the in
our world.
It will be not an easy task in itself.
I mean like the one we we had with the
dotnet runtime garbage collection similar
and the output is basically.
The expected output is.
Document or a code may may be also a
running system in principle which the
which is basically mostly generated using
the AI.
OK,
so that's the A I output and that's part
of the submission.
And this is what you think.
It would have been a good submission
generated by the A I,
but of course it can be 100 pages that
you didn't write.
They are AI generated plus.
We're not looking for the logs,
please of your prompts,
but basically the most significant
prompts that you believe have been
fundamental for generating the results.
In the results.
Because as I often say,
the important thing is make posing the
right question to get a good answer and
with Andrea we will try to evaluate your
prompt, not of course also the output,
because if the output.
Is modest,
then you didn't use it properly the eye
because nowadays with the eye you should
be able to produce a super wonderful
outputs and the third thing that will be
asked that.
4 is how did you check the output to
ensure that what is submitted is correct?
These are the three elements were
released, let's say by December the 10th.
The the list of projects which is not
closed.
You will only have to tell us the number,
the project number you intend to.
Uh.
To do,
I don't see any particular advantage in
picking up the same all the class simply
because the AI uses random generation,
so for sure any output will be for sure
different than any other output,
so I will discourage.
Personally to try to to trick this part,
you're already relying on the on on the
eye for for your work.
But basically when you justify when you
discuss the output from that.
It should emerge that you did the right
checks.
So should imagine I I checked this
because to the output this is crucial and
so I double check it then I double check
it this way.
I mean and we will have some examples
starting from today on.
Possible techniques.
Clearly you can ask to more AI models in
the hope that different models are
different in in mistakes.
You can Google and look for answers now
that you have only a fact-chaking task to
do. This is another one.
You can go and study a book and say OK,
studied and found in the in the book that
this is right or wrong.
That's that's OK too.
But nevertheless,
you can follow the resources that the eye
introduces to justify the answer.
But basically you have to prove through
that that you understood what are the
relevant part of any programming related.
Task and you put and you check in the
right thing and we will try to vary.
So there will be broad projects,
very focused project so that if you like
to dig down you will get some
satisfaction.
If you want to learn how to browse a
super big code base,
that will be welcome too.
And so that's basically the idea.
And of course, as part of the submission,
I respect also to know which models you
decided to use to.
If you don't find your lifetime project
in the least,
you're very welcome to submit your
favorite project to me and.
Yeah, and we'll be more than gladly.
Will be very prone to accept if it's
reasonable.
By reasonable we we mean a it's the
workload is OK and compatible with the
size of the exam. It's not too simple,
but it's not even too hard because part
of the class typically is many students
that are passionate and sometimes they
start for journeys that are totally.
Unfortunate with respect to the workload
that required to pass the exam,
which is pointless honestly. So I mean,
but if you want to do something related
that you consider worth of your export
including software development that you
want to.
With the methodology that I just
described, you want to put in practice,
you're more than welcome. And I mean,
I think if you study and do something
interesting,
usually it's a good motivation and
hopefully the reason because you're still
here instead of.
Looking for a job somewhere else, right?
So having said that.
Uh, as the first exercise.
First of all, I have to get.
I will uh use charge EPT uh.
Just because uh.
Roger, please.
Exit size 1.
Web exploring.
Web assembly.
Um.
Uh, we've.
Plus we want to explore.
Uh, Webassembly technology.
Uh, don't uh give up.
Uh.
Oh L.
Has to find that information to truly
understand.
OK,
so this is in general is a good thing
when you start to chart to.
Give some instructions, yeah.
OK.
Mm-hmm.
I'm not sure I want to go through all the
details, but nevertheless,
at least what is web?
How many of you are aware about
Webassembly? Hands up.
But basically what, uh, I didn't expect.
So Webassembly is an open standard.
That defines a portable binary code is
basically the JVM designed to be run
inside the web browser.
So that's basically and and the goal was
basically to be able to run computer
games of similar inside the web.
Browser where having the canvas or
changes to the Dom performance that is
not acceptable for some workload.
Let's say computer games is a good
example, but not the only one.
Oh yeah, sorry.
Thank you.
It was initially designed to enable high
performance coding web browsers.
Rather than only in JavaScript,
that was basically the idea.
OK, so um, let's leave.
The too long answer here and let's start
trying to understand that.
So if you want to understand the
technology such as Webassembly,
what would you ask?
And this is an open question.
To the AI.
Hmm.
Can you give me the link to a significant
web assembly application or example?
I want to be impressed.
OK.
May we city bomb against?
Hmm.
Capcut web.
Let's let's go for.
Um.
Actually, he's changed the.
Igma.
OK.
Let's go so.
The DPO will not be happy about that.
Don't give your identity.
OK.
Yeah, let let me go away. I mean,
Figma is OK, but.
Let me go back.
I was looking more Google Earth uses as
you can see.
There are a number of uh.
If I converted.
Let's use this fractal editor.
Just because he's small enough.
OK, performance is not bad,
so if we go to.
10,000.
Iterations.
Performance is not bad at all.
Um,
just uh to understand uh what you're
looking to. Um,
do you know how this set is computed?
Very, very short answer basically is.
There is a mathematical definition in the,
so you're looking at a representation of
a complex plane,
so it works with complex numbers.
Uh, so every point here has a.
Complex coordinates of real and imaginary
parts.
And basically you start a recursive
equation which is Z is equal square of Z
+ C where C is the original value.
So you start with this point and we'll
have some.
Coordinates those that you can see down
there and basically you raise to the
square, you add the the the point itself.
And you keep going.
So if the sequence does not diverge,
which basically stays below 2.
Then the the sequence,
the point belongs to the Mandel Brosette
and it's paint in black.
Uh.
If the iteration for the single point
diverts in the sense that goes beyond two
in module,
which basically is the square modular is
4,
then that will diverge to infinite
product and so you count how many
iteration and you.
Pick up the color, uh,
according to the number of iterations, uh,
it took to diverge.
So basically when I say.
10,
000 or so iteration means that for every
black point the system computed 10,
000 square root plus a complex number and
so of course the more you zoom.
Good.
There are a few elements,
but basically the more black you see,
the more computation that it would be
required and the more iteration because
of course in principle.
A point may diverge very far in the
sequence,
and so typically the definition set is
until the infinite the approximation that
if you stay under the threshold long
enough.
It will be part of the set and so if you
increase increase the the iteration you
will get better representation of the set
and typically a better resolution and
this generates a.
Very beautiful images,
but as you can see it's now,
so if I go to the maximum.
On the laptop is suffering,
but nevertheless the performance is
reasonable. If I do it this in JavaScript,
it will take probably 10 times or so
because the number processing is made by
the interpreter, not by.
Something that is compiled.
Here below there there is another Julia
is another set similar approach,
so similar story, different equation OK.
I think it's uh uh good enough to as an
example of uh.
How to warm up my my laptop? OK,
now that we know, I mean, OK,
it's impressive,
but we we learned also that Figma,
Google Earth and other technologies are
using this.
What is the next question you will have?
I mean this is the ADVANCED PROGRAMMING
poster, so please interesting questions.
Why were assembly was necessary and what
led to its development?
Excellent question. Thank you.
The problem JavaScript is the only
execution engine on the web,
but that was basically the problem and
there are applications that are not
really.
Efficient.
In 2013,
and I still remember it when I first
compiled, there was this ASMJS.
You may have heard it.
That was pretty wow.
ASMJS was the the first attempt and was
basically the idea was let's define a
subset of JavaScript that can can be
statically typed.
Let us say that you can infer the types
of a subset of JavaScript and let's
compile it in assembly, OK.
And they were, um.
Pretty impressive examples. They use LLBM.
LLBM was made popular by the ASM JS story
quite a lot because one of the first part
was to a port from C++.
To JavaScript using em script and that
was implemented with LLVM and so
basically it was possible to run C++
programs that use a Web GL.
Right into the web browser and that led
to the point which where it was possible
to come to cross compile an entire game
engine.
Production game,
the game engine down to web to AS and JS.
So it was possible to have console like
computer games running on the web browser.
Mozilla Foundation was behind this this
first attempt.
So clearly that was a a good thing,
but nevertheless you have to be sure that
you you wrote the right subset.
So the advantage was that any browser
would have been able to interpret that
thing.
But of course you were not sure that
everything would have been compiled by a
particular web browser,
but that was basically the first idea.
Uh, Chrome. Uh, introducing the NACL.
It was basically binary code sandbox it
as it was in the original Java and that
was another and so after two years of
wonderful.
Examples when I use it to teach.
I use it to show the banana bread game
made by Mozilla Foundation using ACM JS
and it was super cool and at some point
someone said let's define a standard and
so.
And so.
A collaboration between Mozilla,
Google and Microsoft and Apple,
which means Webkit.
Chrome.
Uh and Safari.
So most of the HTML renders to get us uh
to reach a standard that is known as uh.
The web are sending.
So specification binary instruction
format.
So let's compile because clearly parsing
is expensive and if the project is large
then it will be more expensive,
especially if in the project you have to
deploy also.
Data. So if you think of a computer games,
a computer game is basically not so much
code for the core.
Dom manipulation part and a lot of data
because you have to load the meshes and
other structures to the point in which
the loader of this data structure is a
crucial point in a computer game engine.
And and so being binary makes a lot of
sense,
because if you have megabytes and
megabytes of code,
then the parsing will be expensive.
Oh, that's interesting.
Stack based vitro machine.
Deterministic performance.
This is another goal.
So you want to make a computer game.
The JIT and the garbage collector have
some drawbacks. We learned that.
You may be unlucky because you the first
time you run a method,
you trigger the jit. In general,
the little bit of overhead in jitting is
neglectable. You don't really care.
And so for the average computer program,
you can tolerate the system that compiles
itself during the execution. That's OK,
that's easy,
but if you are running a computer game.
Code or video processing,
processing data from a camera, a robot,
etcetera.
Then even the small lag may introduce
glitches in case of a computer games or.
Data frame loss in a uh real time
applications.
OK and so the determinacy performance
clearly is uh it was an interesting goal.
Safety, of course.
I don't think you'd like to open a web
page and get your computer erased or
worse.
Compatible with JavaScript,
so there should be some way to call
JavaScript etcetera.
And that was important because the
typical scenario is a mixed scenario,
so where you have.
Part of the rendering running the code,
plus the ability to call JavaScript and
modify the Dom so that you can have a
non-critical part of your system made
with traditional HTML and Dom
manipulation instead of having.
To compile everything, standardize the.
And now it's almost 10 years there,
so it's a fairly important technology.
Why performance gap between JS and
Nativco? Lack of language diversity,
so the the need to be able to write in
any language.
So we need to be able to write compilers
to this thing.
Security concern if you use native code
portability because a bytecode can be
cross compiled and.
Now, until few years ago,
probably we wouldn't say that that was
important,
but we all know that we run different
architectures ARM.
X86 another one.
Hmm.
Risk 5 is a,
I mean a growing platform backed by
European Union that hopefully eventually
will produce some interesting silicon,
but even less is a different as a
different instruction set than ARM and
X86.
So we're going back in a word in which
depending on.
The device you have,
you may have a different instruction set
and so the portability of the bytecode is
important because otherwise you should
produce a compiled version for each
architecture so.
That's unopen with the fall of X86.
Now we're living in a world which is very
different than it was 10 years ago. Slow,
slow times parsing.
Uh, and productivity, OK.
That's those are OK, next question.
OK,
that will be a a possible course of
action,
but before there I think going there.
So to say OK,
I want to do a project or I want to
develop for this thing,
we're we're in the advanced programming
course, so.
If we want to understand how this
technology is implemented,
which was will be the next question.
How it works, Sir?
How it works is a a typical example of a
of a question that you. I mean,
let's try it, but.
Typically is is a good example of a high
level question that likely will produce a
high level answer which will not add the
significant knowledge to you.
If you attended the advanced programming
force.
O.
Was not a stack.
You start from high level language.
Yeah, this is.
A text representation of the binary
format.
And the execution model.
So you get some information better than I
would have expected,
probably by the question that I asked
before the answer was specific.
But the risk you have when you ask how it
works is that you will not get this.
The level of detail you will need to
fully understand the thing you were
proposing.
OK, so this is an interesting.
Line uh of thought. Uh.
Nevertheless,
the answer was much better than I would
have. I would have expected too much.
This AI is getting too smart.
So can you compare was?
We've JVM by code.
Look at the start of the answer after you
last prompt explains you why it is so.
Oh yeah, OK, so thanks.
This chart is in the project advanced
programming and the reason I had the
instructions that this is about advanced
programming. So.
Clearly the answer.
If you try to get how it works in a
non-advanced programming,
probably you will get a much. Oh,
it's nice.
You get this example and then you get a
toy example which is basically useless.
Thank you.
Can you compare Wasman with by code and
ILCLR?
Sierra.
I should have used it and not advance it
for me.
OK.
By the way, of course,
if you start your chat by saying I am a
student of advanced programming course
and this is the syllabus, etcetera,
then you keep going on,
you can you basically will get a similar
context, OK.
So uh.
Multi language plus for independent year.
Hmm.
Compilation pipeline.
So WebAssembly in Rust,
you go through the LLVM IR,
you get the Wasm, the browser.
JVM works with this CLIL. OK,
I was thinking about the instruction set.
I guess and suggestion was I want to
understand that the machine is pretty
natural to understand the instruction set.
So it's a type of the stack machine.
OK,
type stack machine with object oriented
in this case is minimal low level. OK,
this is a bit of information which is
interesting and it hints that.
Probably there are no types and objects
at the WASP level,
whereas in CLR and JVM we learn that
there is runtime type information to
support reflection.
Similar number of operations around 200.
Instruction types primitive,
so it's interesting to see that there are
explicitly mentioning the precision of
integers and and floating points.
Clearly this has been designed to support.
Games or numerical processing type system
simple.
OK.
How old you?
Uh.
Interpret this simple.
I will probably,
I mean my understanding in terms of the
things that we discussed during the
course is no type constructors.
Probably.
And perhaps I this is an item that I will
bookmark my in my head and say, OK,
let's go and check whether I'm right.
And it it it's true that it's simple
means this.
But to me probably is it's like a Python
or or JavaScript.
I mean you have a fixed set of types and
and then you use syntaxes sugaring to
give the impression you have that
constructor,
but there are no really new types that
you can define in those languages.
As opposed does javaor.
net where you have type constructors,
inheritance, parametric polymorphism,
etcetera. Statically type. OK,
reasonable for efficiency,
but now we know what exactly means.
Value oriented.
How would you interpret the value
oriented?
And not rather object than not references
value oriented to me.
But again,
this is another that I think we will have
to dig farther, but nevertheless, to me.
Make me think of struct of C++ or or of
CI mean value semantics,
copy semantics when you pass things
around.
This also let me think that probably.
There is little garbage collection or no
garbage collection or whatever it is.
So OK,
I am to think how we know that we have
also to investigate the memory model
because.
We know that Nojit,
but we still have to understand the the
rest.
Memory model linear memory contiguous
byte array.
Another interesting aspect.
Notice by the way,
I of course I did explore.
Webassembly. I never explore this way.
Webassembly. OK,
so I'm finding things I didn't know.
And that's,
I mean I I picked up this as a as an
exercise to be on par.
So I mean I have no real idea where I'm
going,
what I'm getting as you would when you
will do your project, I mean.
The goal is we want to explore assembly
and understands all the bits and bytes
and maybe even have access to the source
code to cross check something something
no and there are already.
Interesting part that I just skipped it
because I didn't. I was interesting yet,
but it's interesting to see that was
where there is this LLBM element for
compilation to get the the the web
assembly.
Which is something that probably you
would like to dig down. OK, let's go. Oh,
there was also comment.
Mm.
Where I was.
I skip this and this is oh, where I was.
Oh yeah, here. Um.
Safety mechanics.
Static validation plus sandboxing.
No row pointers,
so we know that there are no pointers in
which you can work around them.
OK.
So wasma is closer to a typed assembly
language.
Basically you would expect more like a a
machine assembly than a higher level
virtual machine. OK.
Apparently from the question I also got
the natural answer includes the
instructions but also type system.
So the object model is none.
Until was garbage collection proposals
measure.
So we learned that there are proposals
for a garbage collection support in was
not but for for the moment no.
No object model question why the object
model relates to the garbage collection?
But this comment please the relates the
absence of objects with the garbage
collection. Why?
You're moving around the right spot.
Let's try to to say it better. I mean,
yes, C++ has no garbage collection.
We said that there was an implementation
which is imprecise.
Because what you need to have a garbage
collector.
Yeah, object values.
What is the first phase of any collector?
The mark phase.
You want to mark the memory and you must
be able to prove that potentially that
memory is reachable.
The the the the rest of the memory which
is not market has not been marketed.
That will be unreachable and you can free
for for sure because it's not needed
anymore.
That's the basis of any collection.
OK, you you start from the roots,
you mark all the objects and say OK,
if I'm able starting from the roots to
mark all an object that potentially that
maybe access it in the future,
so I cannot safely.
They allocated.
So this is the reason because I mean my
personal take away about this comment is
until so when there will be a garbage
collector then some formal object model
may be simpler without type construction.
Factor will be needed because you need to
be able to know the layout of the memory
objects in order to be able to garbage
collect.
And so probably the two things in some
document that the AI read,
they are related. Then it makes sense, OK.
Um.
OK.
Perspective is also reasonable.
When we say that it's the the reference
that you need for. Yeah,
that that's of course. Thank you, Andrea.
Yeah.
They're looking to talk to the PD with
the records.
Yeah, yeah, no,
that that's another big point,
which also means that with the current
Webassembly,
probably you have to implement your own
GC.
If you need dynamic memory,
which everybody does, so that's.
That's probably part of that,
but so remembering the the origin of
ASMJS,
it was really called numerical code,
the meshes and this kind of things.
So it was very not object oriented.
And not dynamically allocated memory.
So inheritance, no reflection, no.
Exception. We're working on that.
In your opinion,
why the A I decided to put exception as a
dimension? Why exceptions?
We didn't speak much about exceptions.
Also in the runtime, but I mean from.
On what we've learned that why exceptions
are worth having a dedicated slot in this
list.
So when you throw an exception in your
program.
What happens at runtime, in your opinion?
You can tell me that uh.
You have to go back.
Until you find a cash close and if no
cash close is found,
you terminate the program with an
exception.
That would probably be your answer in
terms of definition,
but from the runtime perspective,
what happens in your opinion?
When you throw an exception.
With respect to the normal execution.
So.
Which which data structure of the runtime
will be involved?
Hmm.
Yeah, my listener, uh, is uh.
No, I wouldn't say no. I mean,
it's very specific.
Of the runtime.
So the runtime structures that we learn
are important are the heap.
We don't have heap then.
Stack plus a few others. So the stack.
What happens to the stack when you throw
an exception?
You have to unwind the stack,
which is a tremendous operation,
especially with the semantics of Java and.
net with the finally clause.
That is super complicated. I mean,
it's something we didn't discuss too much.
My bad,
but it's a complex process because
basically you have to alter the natural
flow of execution and you have to clean
up the runtime state to the point in
which the execution execution restarts.
In a consistent set of stack and heap
states. OK,
so that's that is basically violating the
natural code execution flow.
And up front and it can't be implemented
inside the runtime.
I mean inside the language.
That is something that requires a runtime
implementation because you you must be
able to jump out of three function calls
or method calls.
And unwind the stack before resuming the
execution in some other point in.
In in C it is possible to implement
exceptions.
In fact any good program C programmer did
implement exceptions.
How? Anyone knows?
Hmm.
So jump a long jump. Yeah,
so C as a dedicated functions coming from
the runtime that allows you basically to
take a picture of the registers and the
state of the CPU and you can restore them
and with that you can implement.
Exceptions and also threads.
And in fact the P threads originally were
implemented by using set jump and long
jump. Yes, correct answer, right.
OK and garbage collection, no.
Manual or custom via runtime?
OK, we learn something.
I say Webassembly is very smaller as a
virtual machine with respect to.
net and memory flat linear memory buffer.
Isolation each module.
So there are modules we just learned no
shared heap unless imported exported.
So sandboxing that exchange so.
There are these implicit import exports
that are curious as a mechanism,
so let's keep in our mind that it it may
be interesting. OK,
I will skip binary size, etcetera.
Uh, porting easy. Uh.
Philosophical some money.
Um.
OK,
you get also conceptual analogy for
students.
This is because the in the structure and
said that this project is dedicated to
preparing the and so there are comments
for students. OK, yes.
Today we also have some problems to like
set up the environment, which were, yeah,
for example,
you could say that the environment that
we're using now has had some set up
before we started the project.
I hate possibly for first so you can
where to somehow like it's been said
before set up something I'm a student I'm
talking to research and I want the
information like some some that blog.
Yeah, but I mean,
so and this brings to next question,
what is the?
So we learn about the memory model,
we learn about the instructions and
general abilities. We will be.
Your next question.
A lot of we had a lot of details.
We're like supposed but not completely
explained what they were not clear in.
What is not clear? No, no,
it's not not more only in time,
not formally. Yeah, but I mean.
So, sorry,
I don't know who the people online
distance to the students. Oh,
is able to visit us.
So maybe you should repeat, yeah.
OK, so you're right, Andrea.
So we were discussing about.
So the point was we don't have yet a
formal model.
That was basically the point.
And so the would you suggest me to ask if
there is a formal definition?
Because we know there is a standard,
so the standard implies formal definition.
You you can say OK uh where is uh define
under the standard?
Can you find me the link?
That was basically.
What is it like?
It's OK. It's simple types.
The the hypothesis was there is no
definition. Oh yeah,
but actually that was before I was
finding in the table downwards there were
no types.
And so I said, OK,
the answer is already there.
I don't ask it. You're right.
In my mind I did say OK,
I have to remember to ask about type if
there are no type constructor.
But few tables later we found that the
answer was no,
there are no type constructors,
no objects, no nothing.
OK,
so here we found that we got the URL of
the specifications.
Other question that will mean I mean.
We learned that is a stack based machine.
Do you think that there are interesting
question that we can ask about the
bytecode?
I will say because so far about the
bytecode we learned that there are just
200 instructions which is pretty much the
same number as JVM.
And CLR,
do you think that there are interesting
questions that we can pose?
I mean that that that's something that
not me, but if you want you can ask for.
But can you show me an example?
Of Mandelbrot function implementation in
use.
Instruction of use of.
Let's try like this I I hope.
They will.
So the iteration in Mandelbrot is fairly
easy, is numerical,
and it helps us to see a number of things.
I mean, there is some arithmetics,
there is a loop, there is an if so.
It's a an easy loop to get a flavor of
what how the the the assembly looks like.
Because it's OK,
I mean to have general notion,
but from time to time it's nice also to
have some examples to get the flavor of
the thing.
Actually.
OK,
so module from from what we learn with
Webassembly is defined by modules that
are my understanding is they are similar
to DLL so that you can have different.
Uh,
precompiled assembly that can be reused.
Anyone is calling me?
Um.
So what can we?
So we we learned that you can define
functions on the level of the machine.
Which is.
This is clearly a comment,
so the comments assumes that you have.
2 floating points that are the complex
numbers and the integer,
the maximum number of iterations and the
result is the number of iteration before
diverging or not.
OK. And this is so.
The declaration.
So at least we know that in web assembly
we got functions.
And the result is an I32.
And then what is this?
OK, variables. OK,
so this let us think that the machine.
As a stack frame and so basically it is
able to implement the activation record
logic at runtime. OK block.
Loop.
These names.
I don't know well,
so we will then I I still have open
questions, so I mean.
This is a block. OK,
I can leave that this dollar exit.
So it looks like that they at least the
AI because clearly the AI here is helping
to decode something that is binary.
So it's not like Java where you have the
literal defined in the in the standard
and then the byte code representation.
In this case is a text representation
that I'm not sure is a standard.
We have also to check that,
but nevertheless.
And this dollar seems to be the label in
the in the language.
This is my my take away.
So there there is a loop.
And what can we get from this brief?
Branch shift exit.
So the model of the virtual machine is
the branching model is similar to javaand.
net so you don't have a while or repeat
until the construct.
You can jump to a label.
I will add that these labels should be
contained into the into the function
because otherwise the code will meet type
safe and so in java in.net is the same.
You cannot jump outside of the method. OK,
it's just the way.
You uh.
OK, so.
Uh, you branch to exit.
And.
And here we have greater or equal. Yes,
I don't know.
And you get the local variable I,
you get the local variable Max and and
then you compare them and you decide OK.
Right,
let's look something more interesting.
This one. Oh, this is if the square,
the square of the two numbers you just
computed is greater than 4.
You escaped, so break, you go outside.
Let's look at these.
Why this is interesting?
Because it tells you how the virtual
machine you are studying implements
arithmetics,
which is a big part of any computer
program.
So OK,
the local set temp clearly in this pseudo
code local tells you which the set
instruction refers to a local variable.
So the prefix looks this is a a float 64
operation addition.
Um.
So something which is a piece from this
is that operations are not using an
operand stack as it is in Java or in.net.
This is a big difference with respect to
JVM.
And and CLR.
So in CLR and in JVM you will.
There is an operand stack where every
instruction of virtual machine
accumulates logically, of course.
This is after it will be compiled,
so it's just for defining the computation.
So in in.
When you let's say the let's take this,
this multiplies by two.
Oh, let me check. OK, no,
let let me take this.
So multiply ZR and ZI.
OK, so in.
net in Java that will be load local ZR,
load local ZI, mod multiply. OK,
so basically the logic in instructions is
you have instructions to load the
operating stack.
And then you call multiply and the result
will push will be pushed if there is a
result on the open stack.
So that's the way they work from.
At least from this syntax we may derive
that.
The Webassembly takes as an approach
something more like a machine assembly in
which operations have arguments and you
have to pass.
You call the operation and the arguments
and you get the results.
Oh, me too.
So yeah.
No.
So it's I just found it's not the
rendering because apparently there is the
what is WebAssembly text is a standard
and there is even a tool that allows you
to compile it down to the binary.
So apparently this is a standard way to
express things.
Um.
I thought that.
The was machine used a local operands.
Stack.
But from the what?
Looks like, uh, operations have uh,
humans and uh, they don't.
Get them from the open stack.
Yeah.
What is the?
Uh was real approach.
Is just the water.
That uh.
The way or also the wasp.
OK, this is a a nice, I mean, um.
As you can see, as you start digging down.
Question gets more complicated, OK,
because then now we get a general review,
but we want to be precise in our
derivation.
We want to check that we learn the right
thing, not.
A logical presentation or whatever.
And in fact now it's not excellent.
It's fantastic question.
So Webassembly is indeed a stack machine.
Every instruction conceptually pops this
operand from an operand stack and pushes
results back onto it.
OK.
So why? What looks different? Professor,
this is the answer we're looking for.
So we just learned that the textile
representation of the assembly is not
one-on-one.
Uh with the uh the the bytecode.
OK,
so basically to help people reading the
text, this is the way it will work,
but the WebAssembly text supports also.
Functional view to help reading the code,
which of course it's harder to read for
humans with the low push and pop,
push and pop.
You have to reconstruct that.
Yeah, exactly.
The sugaring is very powerful.
Yeah,
and in fact this is the wasma will be
something like get local, get local,
add and OK.
Statically typed.
I think it was fairly obvious because the
operations basically when you.
Define the locals and you assigns the
locals. You use constants of a type.
So clearly the compiler is perfectly able
to statically associate a type to every
local and then you explicitly say.
The type expected by the operation and so
therefore if you buy like the type you
you are clearly able to tell a like like
in the J way instruction for different
yeah so there will be.
F32 dot add the I32 yeah.
But this is true for JVM and also for CLR.
It's clearly all these intermediate
language are taught for as a second step
from a compiler.
So I mean there's no real value.
Uh in in having uh uh overloaded
operations because uh it is machine
generated code.
It doesn't force you to update the the
world when we need to apply exactly.
OK.
OK,
we we got a treaty on why you get both
syntaxes available,
but basically we found the answer to.
To our questions,
other interesting questions.
I have at least one.
What is the entry point of?
That I think it would be a reasonable
question.
All excessive excellent questions.
And the answer is there is no entry point
because it is basically a component which
efficiently runs binary bytecode in
modules and the execution is triggered
from outside.
But thank you for the question,
because that would have been the other
area of interest of the WASMA machine.
So there are two letters entry start
section, so in some case you can.
In fact, start or exported function,
host controller data,
so the caller and I would like to say
probably that is the natural way.
So the host of the Webassembly component
will decide.
To invoke any function inside the the
modules. OK.
This is an example Webassembly initiate
streaming fetch.
And then exports main 42 and you will get
the execution of main. OK,
this brings to another interesting aspect
that if you really want to understand the
runtime,
in this case we are studying a runtime.
It's OK to ask about the memory,
about the instruction, the types, scoping.
We did use it that that was fairly easy
because it's using function.
So in static scoping and value pass by
value semantics.
So I didn't dig farther because.
It was pretty easy to understand,
but there is another crucial aspect which
is interoperability,
because the programming language gives
you the logical computation,
but resources are owned by external
entities.
A process through the operating system
calls gives you access to the operating
system resources.
The Webassembly probably will give you
access to some external resources
provided by the web browser,
which is its natural container.
O.
I think it will be interesting
interesting to how was interrupt with its
its host.
Works.
That will be probably the first question
I will pose.
Excellent.
OK.
So when a WES model is instantiated,
WebAssembly runtime browser node was
creates an isolated environment. No Cisco,
no IO, no nothing.
OK And in fact they said the memory is a
bytecode array, so it's not the memory,
it's a data structure.
OK,
everything external must be provided by
the host. So this is a security measure.
So there there are no mechanism.
All the resources should be provided
allowed by the host.
Which embeds the component.
The host defines what functional memories
are imported into the model.
A WebAssembly module define import things
in needs and exports things it provides.
Example so it import.
A host function log from the module
environment and it exports the double
function.
O in JavaScript.
OS provided there. OK,
so you fetch the module.
And you go in the module,
you go into the exports and you invoke
the function and you pass the argument.
And the imports.
Alright.
Specify here.
So basically you decide that what can be
called from the the web assembly and what
you can call from the web assembly. OK,
so it is.
Perhaps this is one of the reason because
you don't really need a cheat,
because the well assembly seems to be
designed to define functions that
requires that benefits from compilations.
So whenever you go and invoke that is
that is a function that is computational
intensive,
then you cannot flow then execute
basically the compiled version,
and in this sense you don't, you're not.
Defining the full system into the web
assembly,
but only the portions of code that that
will benefit from from this of course
when the WASM.
Uh.
Invoke the log function.
You will pay some price because clearly
if you invoke the log function internally,
you have to ask to the host.
Pass the value so that you you have
marshalling of parameters,
then the host will execute the function
and eventually you will go back and you
have to marshal back the result.
And so there may be some serialization
deserialization, but being so low level.
This is unlikely because typically you
will ask for numbers and return numbers,
which are the only data types that uh we
uh.
We've seen so far. You may even get, oh,
um, that's another interesting question.
Has was strings. I would expect so.
What are string operands?
Why are interesting?
Why it is interesting to ask about
screens?
Because they have a viable size.
Now we live in a world after Java that
made us to think that you can sum up
strings easily because basically strings
are immutable and you keep copying.
Uh, bytes, but before Java.
I still remember when I was a student,
both in Pascal and C,
to have spent a lot of time to write code
to to do the string concatenation memory
allocation to ensure that the buffer was
good, big enough, etcetera. OK, so.
Yes,
strings are interesting because they have
variable size.
I get excellent again. Thank you.
So there we are.
Only these primitive value types.
So there are no string, no characters,
no nothing.
Interesting that there is an optional.
Extension with 128 bit.
16 bytes vector that can be efficiently
implemented in GPU for SIM computations.
Do you know what SIM stands for?
SIMD stands for Single Instruction
Multiple Data.
OK.
And it is basically the core concept
around GPU computing. So when you pay $50,
000 for a GPU,
you're getting a SIM machine.
So a machine in which you say I want to
add and I have a list of several numbers
in input and several numbers pay wise and
you get the the and and the the machine
basically execute the same instruction to
all the data.
Cinder has become really popular
originally because of 3D graphics,
thanks to computer gamers,
because in computer games,
in 3D especially,
it is fairly common to have to multiply
and sum a lot of numbers.
That are representing points in the 3D
space.
And then of course linear algebra is made
of arrays and operation that you want to
do perform on vectors or matrices and
therefore.
2005 more or less,
NVIDIA had the great idea to say, OK,
let's use the GPU that has been optimized
for 3D graphics to perform linear algebra
computations.
And apparently that started the CUDA and
then.
High performance computation uh uh have
become possible.
And neural networks complicated the a
little bit more the scenario because.
Uh, the new GPUs.
Are not supporting anymore the 64 bit
precision floating points because that in
the neural networks how precision is good
enough, so 16 bits even less.
So the new with the GPU's for AI are
basically designed.
Physicists are not happy about this have
transistors having more.
F32 and even F16 to to do SIM,
but it's interesting that there is 128
bits vector data structure.
No string char booler struct as another
proof that this is not a general part of
virtual machine,
but it's just a machine to have functions
that the browser is capable of compile
and execute efficiently.
That's the only purpose of this thing,
which is something that is not so evident
when you read the documentation,
high level document,
even from the tables we got from the eye,
it wasn't that evident that actually is
not so general.
The WASMA is fairly restricted,
so I think this is a good finding that is
worth and of course and I will leave it
to you as an exercise.
How would you check that these statements
we we've drawn, I mean statically type,
no type constructors, only integer number,
number or vector types, etcetera?
False true.
We need a way to check this,
so I encourage you to devise a way the
way you will double check the output of
the eye. Because I mean, as you can see,
these tables are so nice that you may be
tempted to think, oh, it's like a book.
Should be true,
but as we've learned a few classes ago,
you can get a decision and it may be nice
and false.
So we need a way to cross check our
findings so.
Assignment.
Start thinking how would you validate all
the facts that we found in the last two
hours?
Any comments or questions or anything?
You're welcome.
What? No.
So the the typical the typical way.
So the question is.
How do we write Webassembly?
Typically you will use some cross
compiler. There are several.
Emscripten is 1 popular,
which basically takes C++ and allows you
to get what as the output.
So makes no sense. So that's, uh,
that that's the typical.
OK. So if there are no other questions,
thank you. Have a nice weekend.